Register of the Jacques Leprette papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Jacques Leprette papers
1913-2006
2006C17
Hoover Institution Archives
209 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize boxes (85.2 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports, conference and meeting materials, printed matter, and audiovisual material, relating to French foreign relations; French participation in the European Economic Community, European Union and other European organizations; French participation in the United Nations and other international organizations; French relations with other Francophone countries; international law; and human rights.
Leprette, Jacques.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2006.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1920 Born, Alexandria, Egypt
1940-1941 Mobilized and serves in French army
1941 Evacuated to Algeria, where he studied law
1943 Enlisted in Foreign Legion
1944-1945 Landed with French forces in Provence. Wounded in the Battle of Belfort, then participated in campaigns in Alsace, Germany, and Austria
1947 Graduated from the Ecole Nationale d'Administration, Paris. Joined French foreign ministry as member of its European department Author, Le statut international de Trieste
1949-1952 Counselor, Council of Europe, Strasbourg, France
1952-1955 Head, political division, French military government in Berlin, Germany
1955-1959 First secretary, French embassy, Washington, D.C.
1959-1961 Head of European Community affairs service, French foreign ministry, Paris, France
1961-1964 French ambassador to Mauritania
1964-1966 Director of interministerial liaison service, French information ministry, Paris, France
1966-1971 Minister-counselor, French embassy, Washington, D.C.
1971-1975 Director responsible for affairs concerning the United Nations and international organizations, French foreign ministry, Paris, France
1975-1976 Associate director for political affairs, French foreign ministry, Paris, France
1976-1982 French ambassador to the United Nations and permanent representative on the Security Council, New York City
1982-1985 French ambassador to the European Community, Brussels, Belgium
1984 Elevated to the rank of Ambassador of France
1985-1989 Organized conferences and summit meetings relating to the international Francophone community
1987 Awarded title of Commandeur, Legion d'Honneur
1988-1990 French representative to U.N. Human Rights Commission, Geneva, Switzerland
1994-1995 Author, Une clef pour l'Europe. Book is awarded Prix des Ambassadeurs and Prix Jean Finot de l'Académie des Sciences Morales et Politiques
1999 Elected member of the Institut de France, Académie des Sciences Morales et Politiques
2002 Awarded title of Grand officier de l'Ordre National du Mérite
2004 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Acquired in 2006, the papers of Jacques Leprette document the life and professional activities of a senior French diplomat, one whose long and distinguished career coincided with the evolution of a newly assertive French foreign policy in the decades following World War II. Occupying a series of important posts, including that of French ambassador to the United Nations, Leprette participated in a number of significant international negotiations and conferences. In particular, his work as a diplomat focused on France's efforts to promote European integration; the role of the United Nations in international peacekeeping; and cooperation among Francophone nations and communities. His papers also shed light on aspects of French political history, especially in the mid-1960s.
Records relating to Leprette's service in the French military during World War II can be found in the Military Career File. The Academic Career File series contains materials relating to Leprette's study of law before and during World War II, as well as to his post-war attendance at the prestigious École nationale d'administration, where he was a member of the first graduating class.
The Speeches and Writings series includes Leprette's many articles and public talks on foreign affairs, as well as those specifically dealing with the United Nations and the nature of international negotiations. This series also includes two monographs: Leprette's doctoral thesis on the status of Trieste after World War II and his book on the construction of European unity, Une clef pour l'Europe.
The Ministère des Affaires Étrangères File groups materials relating to Leprette's various postings as a diplomat and his work as a foreign ministry official in Paris. These materials include correspondence, speeches, and reports and are arranged chronologically under the headings of the specific postings held by Leprette at the time.
Leprette's first posting was as a counselor involved in the negotiations that created the Council of Europe, and the papers include a number of transcripts of the Council's proceedings. His next position was as head of the political department of the French military government in Berlin. Among the materials from this posting are memoranda and bulletins concerning the revolt of East German workers in June 1953, an important event in the early Cold War period.
A significant part of Leprette's subsequent career was spent in the United States, where he served twice at the French embassy in Washington, D.C., first as counselor and then as minister-counselor. In these postings, Leprette was often called upon to explain French foreign policy to American audiences, and the papers contain a number of his speeches on this subject. The materials from these two periods also reveal Leprette's interest in, and appreciation of, American society.
Between his postings in Washington, Leprette served as French ambassador to Mauritania in the years immediately following that country's achievement of independence from France. The papers include a number of reports on the internal situation in Mauritania, including information on opponents of the Ould Daddah regime.
After working at the French foreign ministry as the director of its department for the United Nations and international organizations, Leprette was named as French ambassador to the United Nations. His papers include extensive materials from his participation in the activities of the United Nations, including negotiations on the status of Namibia, the role of U.N. peacekeeping forces in Lebanon, and U.N. Security Council debates on the Iran-Iraq War.
Following his tenure at the United Nations, Leprette became France's ambassador to the European Community in Brussels. Materials from this period include records of meetings and official visits, as well as a dossier made for Leprette in preparation for France's presidency of the European Community in 1984.
One series ( Directeur, Service de Liaison Interministériel pour L'Information File) concerns Leprette's one posting outside of the French foreign ministry, when he worked for Alain Peyrefitte in the French ministry of information. In this capacity, Leprette worked on the 1965 presidential re-election campaign of Charles de Gaulle, and the series contains correspondence, memoranda, and reports relating to the campaign. Peyrefitte remained a close friend of Leprette's, and more of their letters can be found in the Correspondence series.
The Conferences, Seminars, and Official Visits File pertains to the many conferences attended by Leprette, including major ones devoted to relations among Francophone nations and communities, and in which Leprette played a leading role. This series also includes extensive materials concerning seminars on foreign policy at the Académie de la Paix in Monte Carlo and elsewhere.
Leprette's participation in a large number of associations and societies is reflected in the extensive Organizations File. Among these are materials relating to Leprette's election to the Académie des Sciences morales et politiques and to honors he received from the Legion d'Honneur and the Ordre national du Mérite. The series also includes materials relating to Leprette's participation in the affairs of the Fondation et Institut Charles de Gaulle.
The papers also include a small series relating to the published works of Leprette's father, the author Fernand Leprette.
France--Foreign relations.; European communities.; European Economic Community.; European Union.; United Nations--France.; French-speaking countries.; International organization.; International law.; Civil rights.; Diplomats--France.
- Biographical File, 1929-2006
  Scope and Contents note
  Address books, audiovisual material, award programs, bibliography, biographies, catalog, certificate, clippings, date books, diaries and notebooks, genealogical histories, memorial program, obituaries, personal documents, questionnaire, scrapbook materials, and sketches, arranged alphabetically by physical form
  - Address books and directory, 1959-2003 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Audiovisual material, 2004 April 8 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    CD-ROM containing photos depicting the funeral ceremonies for Jacques Leprette, Paris, France
  - Award programs relating to honors given to Jacques Leprette
    - Académie Française, Institut de France, 1988 October 20 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Académie des Sciences Morales et Politiques, Institut de France, 2000 June 23 (Box-folder 1: 4-5)
  - Bibliography of Leprette's writings, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
    Typescript
  - Biographies, 1988-2006 (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Includes "Notice sur la vie et les travaux de Jacques Leprette (1920-2004)," remarks made by Renaud Denoix de Saint Marc, Institut de France, Paris, France, 2006 May 22. Printed copies
  - Catalog offering book by Leprette for sale, 1996 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    Printed copy
  - Certificate of appreciation, 1957 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Clippings, 1963-2002 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Date books
    - 1954 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 2: 5-7)
    - 1962 (Box-folder 3: 1-3)
    - 1963 (Box-folder 3: 4-6)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 4: 7-8)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 4: 10)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 5: 5-6)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 5: 7-9)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 6: 3-6)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 7: 3-5)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 7: 6-7)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 8: 4-6)
    - 1987 (Box-folder 8: 7-8)
    - 1988 (Box-folder 8: 9)
    - 1989 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 9: 1-2)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 9: 3-5)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 9: 7-8)
    - 1994 (Box-folder 9: 9-10)
    - 1995 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)
    - 1996 (Box-folder 10: 3-4)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 10: 5-6)
    - 1998 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - 1999 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - Diaries and notebooks
    - 1948 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - 1949 (Box-folder 11: 2)
    - 1950 (Box-folder 11: 3)
    - 1952 (Box-folder 11: 4)
    - 1966-1968 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 11: 6)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Genealogical histories of the Guitel family
    - 1970 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    - 2000 (Box-folder 12: 1)
  - Memorial program, 2004 (Box-folder 12: 2)
  - Obituaries, 2004 (Box-folder 12: 3)
  - Personal documents
    - Delegate's card, 1948 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - Identity cards, 1941-1949 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Membership cards, 1941-1947 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - Military driver's license, 1943 (Box-folder 12: 7)
    - Passports, 1938-1946 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Savings passbook, 1929 (Box-folder 12: 9)
  - Questionnaire, circa 2002 (Box-folder 12: 10)
    With answers by Leprette regarding his studies at L'École Nationale d'Administration.
  - Scrapbook materials
    - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 12: 11)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 12: 12)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 12: 13)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 12: 14)
    - 1973 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    - 1974 (Box-folder 13: 2)
    - 1975 (Box-folder 13: 3-5)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 13: 6)
    - 1977 (Box-folder 13: 7)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 13: 8)
    - 1978 (Box-folder 14: 1-2)
    - 1979 (Box-folder 14: 3)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 14: 4-7)
    - 1980 (Box-folder 15: 1)
    - 1981 (Box-folder 15: 2-3)
    - 1982 (Box-folder 15: 4-6)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 15: 7)
    - 1983 (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 16: 3-7)
    - 1984 (Box-folder 17: 1-5)
    - 1985 (Box-folder 17: 6)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 17: 7)
    - 1986 (Box-folder 18: 1-2)
  - Sketches by Leprette of Albert Bayet, Konrad Adenauer, and others, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 18: 3)
- Correspondence, 1944-2002
  Christmas cards, invitations, and miscellaneous letters, arranged chronologically; followed by letters, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
  - General
    - Christmas cards
      - 1984-1985 (Box-folder 18: 4)
      - 1986-1997 (Box-folder 18: 5)
    - Invitations, 1985-1998 (Box-folder 18: 6)
    - Letters of congratulation, 1971 (Box-folder 18: 7)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Undated, 1913-2004 (Box-folder 18: 8)
      - 1948-1954 (Box-folder 18: 9)
      - 1971-1974 (Box-folder 19: 1)
      - 1975-1976 (Box-folder 19: 2)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 19: 3)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 19: 4)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 19: 5)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 19: 6)
      - 1981-1982 (Box-folder 19: 7)
      - 1983-1984 (Box-folder 19: 8)
      - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 19: 9)
      - 1987-1988 (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - 1989-1990 (Box-folder 20: 2)
      - 1991-1994 (Box-folder 20: 3)
      - 1995-1996 (Box-folder 20: 4)
      - 1997-2001 (Box-folder 20: 5)
  - Abraham, Ponnu, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 20: 6)
  - Académie de la Paix (René-Jean Dupuy, Claude Nigoul), 1985 (Box-folder 20: 7)
  - Ali, Toyi, 1985 (Box-folder 20: 8)
  - Amram, Philip, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 20: 9)
  - Apied, Jean, 1980 (Box-folder 20: 10)
  - Arnaud, André, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 20: 11)
  - Association des anciens élèves de l'École Nationale d'Administration, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 20: 12)
  - Bagarotti, Giovanni, 1982-1992 (Box-folder 20: 13)
  - Baroody, Lorraine, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 20: 14)
  - Baumel, Jacques, 1989 (Box-folder 20: 15)
  - Beaux, Marcel, 1982-1998 (Box-folder 20: 16)
  - Béliard, Jean, 1996 (Box-folder 20: 17)
  - Benoist, Jean-Marie, 1987 (Box-folder 20: 18)
  - Bise, Elisabeth, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 20: 19)
  - Bona, Dominique, 1987 (Box-folder 20: 20)
  - Bouchard, Lucien, 1994-1996 (Box-folder 20: 21)
  - Bouchet, Paul, 1992 (Box-folder 20: 22)
  - Boutarfa, Abdelmajid, 1988 (Box-folder 20: 23)
  - Boyer, Gaston, 1962-1995 (Box-folder 20: 24)
  - Boyer, Pierre, 1997 (Box-folder 20: 25)
  - Brasseur, Léon, 1962-1968 (Box-folder 20: 26)
  - Bregou, Florence, 1994 (Box-folder 20: 27)
  - Brenas, Jean, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - Bry, Alain, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 21: 2)
  - Castañeda, Jorge, 1985 (Box-folder 21: 3)
  - Chardon, Rémy, 1980-1981 (Box-folder 21: 4)
  - Chesneau, Jean, 1980 (Box-folder 21: 5)
  - Cheysson, Claude, 1968-1985 (Box-folder 21: 6)
  - Clement, Jean-Marc, 1991 (Box-folder 21: 7)
  - Commimes, Guy de, 1996 (Box-folder 21: 8)
  - Cournand, André, 1985 (Box-folder 21: 9)
  - Couve de Murville, Maurice, 1997 (Box-folder 21: 10)
  - Curley, Walter J. P., 1993-1995 (Box-folder 21: 11)
  - Danger, Denise, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 21: 12)
  - Davis, Carole Leprette, 1971-1995 (Box-folder 21: 13)
  - Debré, Michel, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 21: 14)
  - Dejammet, Alain, 1996 (Box-folder 21: 15)
  - Delors, Jacques, 1994 (Box-folder 21: 16)
  - De Tomas Berenguer-Marco, Luis Javier
    - 1995-1999 (Box-folder 21: 17)
    - 2000-2002 (Box-folder 21: 18)
  - Dewast, Philippe, 1995-2000 (Box-folder 21: 19)
  - Druon, Maurice, 1998-2001 (Box-folder 21: 20)
  - Dunlevy, Jerome P., 1984-1985 (Box-folder 21: 21)
  - La Ferrière, Jacques de, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 21: 22)
  - Foksman, Fanny, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 21: 23)
  - Galy, Maurice, 1988 (Box-folder 21: 24)
  - Girard, Christian, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 21: 25)
  - Le Gouguec, Laurence, 1998 (Box-folder 21: 26)
  - Graveleau, Jacques, 1967-1986 (Box-folder 21: 27)
  - Guéna, Yves, 1967-1997 (Box-folder 21: 28)
  - Guiringaud, Louis de, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 21: 29)
  - Guitel, Yvonne, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 21: 28)
  - Hatzfeld, Maud, 1952-1992 (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - Hekking, Francis, 1987 (Box-folder 22: 2)
  - Hessel, Stephane, 1982 (Box-folder 22: 3)
  - Humphrey, Hubert, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 22: 4)
  - International Peace Academy (James H. Binger, Indar Jit Rikhye, Thomas G. Weiss), 1984-1990 (Box-folder 22: 5)
  - Jobert, Michel, 1995 (Box-folder 22: 6)
  - Larminat, François, 1987 (Box-folder 22: 7)
  - Lennuyeux-Comnène, Michel, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 22: 8)
  - Léotard, François, undated (Box-folder 22: 9)
  - Leprette, André, 1944-1984 (Box-folder 22: 10)
  - Leprette, Carina (née Victoria Wilhelmine Carina Sperling)
    - 1948-1950 (Box-folder 22: 11)
    - 1951-1970 (Box-folder 22: 12)
  - Leprette, Christian, 1963-2000 (Box-folder 22: 13)
  - Leprette, Edith and Fernand, 1960-1970 (Box-folder 22: 14)
  - Leprette, François, 1967-1998 (Box-folder 22: 15)
  - Leprette, Pierre, 1944-1983 (Box-folder 22: 16)
  - Leprette, Rémy, 1967-1971 (Box-folder 22: 17)
  - Leprette, Véronique, 1963-1999 (Box-folder 22: 18)
  - Lewin, André, 1994 (Box-folder 22: 19)
  - Louvet, Eric, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 22: 20)
  - Lowenstein, James G., 1977 (Box-folder 22: 21)
  - Lucet, Charles, 1977-2002 (Box-folder 22: 22)
  - Lucet, Jean-Louis, 2002 (Box-folder 22: 23)
  - Lustrac, Jean de, 1966-1973 (Box-folder 22: 24)
  - Maillard, Pierre, 1995-1996 (Box-folder 22: 25)
  - Maniquis, Dalisay, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 23: 1)
  - Matteoli, Jean, undated (Box-folder 23: 2)
  - Melchionni, Grazia, 1997 (Box-folder 23: 3)
  - Ménard, Pierre, 1997 (Box-folder 23: 4)
  - Mertens, Denis, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 23: 5)
  - Messmer, Pierre, 1995 (Box-folder 23: 6)
  - Le Monde (André Fontaine, André Laurens, J. Lesourne), 1987-1996 (Box-folder 23: 7)
  - Monory, René, 1994 (Box-folder 23: 8)
  - Moore, Frank, 1988 (Box-folder 23: 9)
  - Le Morzellec, Joëlle, 1997 (Box-folder 23: 10)
  - Muller, Antigone, 1996 (Box-folder 23: 11)
  - Nagorski, Zygmunt, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 23: 12)
  - Noël, Emile, undated (Box-folder 23: 13)
  - Nouvel Observateur (Jean Daniel), 1998 (Box-folder 23: 14)
  - Novosseloff, Alexandra, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 23: 15)
  - Ollivier, Caroline, 1993 (Box-folder 23: 16)
  - Paczowski, Bohdan and Marie, 1980-1987 (Box-folder 23: 17)
  - Papet, Catherine, 1999 (Box-folder 23: 18)
  - Pellet, Alain, 1978-1990 (Box-folder 23: 19)
  - Pelletreau, Robert, 1989 (Box-folder 23: 20)
  - Pérez de Cuéllar, Javier, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 23: 21)
  - Peyrefitte, Alain
    - 1956-1979 (Box-folder 23: 22)
    - 1980-1999 (Box-folder 23: 23)
  - Pilhes, René, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 23: 24)
  - Pinder, M. L., 1976 (Box-folder 23: 25)
  - Pineau, Blanche, 1996 (Box-folder 23: 26)
  - Piris, Jean-Claude, 1995 (Box-folder 23: 27)
  - Pisani, Edgard, 1986 (Box-folder 23: 28)
  - Plantey, Alain, 1971-1980 (Box-folder 23: 29)
  - Plécy, Anne, undated (Box-folder 23: 30)
  - Puaux, Frédéric, 1996 (Box-folder 23: 31)
  - Rens, Alain, 1996 (Box-folder 23: 32)
  - Revol, Pierre, 1980 (Box-folder 23: 33)
  - Rockefeller, David, 1979 (Box-folder 23: 34)
  - Roucher, Louis, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 23: 35)
  - Ruggiero, Renato, 1995 (Box-folder 23: 36)
  - Runel, Jean, 1966-1969 (Box-folder 23: 37)
  - Santer, Jacques, 1994 (Box-folder 23: 38)
  - Sautter, Christian, 1997 (Box-folder 23: 39)
  - Schonen, Albert de, 1975-2001 (Box-folder 23: 40)
  - Schricke, Jacques, 1962-1978 (Box-folder 23: 41)
  - Schumann, Maurice and Lucie, 1993-1998 (Box-folder 23: 42)
  - Scorzato, Danielle, 1993 (Box-folder 24: 1)
  - Servan-Schreiber, Jean-Claude, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 24: 2)
  - Silguy, Yves-Thibault de, 1998 (Box-folder 24: 3)
  - Sperling, Marie, 1952 (Box-folder 24: 4)
  - Stanley, Richard H., 1990 (Box-folder 24: 5)
  - Stavridi, Zinovia, 1987 (Box-folder 24: 6)
  - Sutterlin, James S., 1977-1991 (Box-folder 24: 7)
  - Tabuteau, Michel, 1957-1978 (Box-folder 24: 8)
  - Tabuteau, Nicolas, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 24: 9)
  - Taittinger, Pierre-Christian, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 24: 10)
  - Torrelli, Maurice, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 24: 11)
  - Touscoz, Jean, 1989 (Box-folder 24: 12)
  - Tricot, Bernard, 1990 (Box-folder 24: 13)
  - UN We Believe (Roger Enloe), 1981 (Box-folder 24: 14)
  - Valère, Edmond, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 24: 15)
  - Van Zandijcke, Bernadette, 1981 (Box-folder 24: 16)
  - Vaurs, Roger, 1960-1986 (Box-folder 24: 17)
  - Vedel, Georges, 1989 (Box-folder 24: 18)
  - Védrine, Hubert, 1997 (Box-folder 24: 19)
  - Verdier, Jacques, 1996 (Box-folder 24: 20)
  - Verluise, Pierre, 1998-1999 (Box-folder 24: 21)
  - Vidal, Jean, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 24: 22)
  - Vignes, Daniel, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 24: 23)
  - Vinci, Piero, 1978 (Box-folder 24: 24)
  - Waldheim, Kurt, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 24: 25)
  - Wilson, Frederick Todd, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 24: 26)
  - Wood, Pia Christina, 1993 (Box-folder 24: 27)
  - Young, Andrew, 1977 (Box-folder 24: 28)
- Speeches and Writings, 1944-2003
  Articles, monographs, and speeches, arranged chronologically
  - "The Question of Trieste,", undated
    - Notes (Box-folder 24: 29)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 24: 30)
  - "Introduction à l'étude du problème allemand,", 1944 October (Box-folder 24: 31)
  - Le statut international de Trieste, 1949 (Box-folder 24: 32)
  - "Le statut de Berlin," Annuaire français de droit international, 1955 (Box-folder 24: 33)
    Correspondence and printed copy
  - "De la Commission des Caraïbes à l'Organisation des Caraïbes," Annuaire français de droit international, 1960 (Box-folder 24: 34)
  - "L'État et l'information," La Revue administrative, 1964 July-August (Box-folder 24: 35)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Le ballotage du Général," unpublished writing on Charles de Gaulle, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 24: 36)
    Notes and printed matter
  - "Marcel Proust: histoire d'une création littéraire,", 1968 February 5 (Box-folder 25: 1)
    Notes
  - Notes on French events of May 1968, 1968 May-June (Box-folder 25: 2)
    Holograph
  - "Marcel Proust: mémoire et réalité," lecture, Alliance Française conference, Washington, D.C., 1969 February 19 (Box-folder 25: 3)
  - "La politique étrangère de la France," speech, Canada, 1973 May 22 (Box-folder 25: 4)
  - "Exposé sur la politique étrangère de la France," lecture, National War College, Washington, D.C., 1975 May 2 (Box-folder 25: 5)
    Background materials, holograph, and typescript
  - "La politique étrangère de la France,", 1975 November 18 (Box-folder 25: 6)
  - "La politique étrangère de la France,", 1976 January 1 (Box-folder 25: 7)
    Correspondence, notes, and reports